<chapter name="HepMC Interface">

<h2>HepMC Interface</h2>

An interface to the HepMC <ref>Dob01</ref> standard event record 
format has been provided by M. Kirsanov. To use it, the relevant 
libraries need to be linked, as explained in the <code>README</code> 
file. Only version 2 of HepMC is supported. (Version 1 requires 
a different interface structure, which was only supported up until 
Pythia 8.107.) 

<p/>
The (simple) procedure to translate PYTHIA 8 events into HepMC ones 
is illustrated in the <code>main41.cc</code>, <code>main42.cc</code>
<code>main61.cc</code> and <code>main62.cc</code>   
main programs. At the core is a call to the
<pre>
HepMC::I_Pythia8::fill_next_event( pythia, hepmcevt, ievnum = -1, convertGluonTo0 = false ) 
</pre>
which takes a reference of the generator object and uses it, on the one
hand, to read out and covert the event record in <code>pythia.event</code> 
and, on the other hand, to extract and store parton-density (PDF) 
information for the hard subprocess from <code>pythia.info</code>. 
The optional last argument, if <code>true</code>, allows you to store 
gluons as "PDG" code 0 rather than the normal 21; this only applies to 
the PDF information, not the event record. 

<p/>
The earlier version of this routine,
<pre>
HepMC::I_Pythia8::fill_next_event( pythia.event, hepmcevt, ievnum = -1 ) 
</pre>
is retained (for now) for backwards compatibility. It takes a PYTHIA event 
as input and returns a HepMC one, but without storing the PDF information. 
The latter could then instead be stored by a separate call
<pre>
HepMC::I_Pythia8::pdf_put_info( hepmcevt, pythia, convertGluonTo0 = false ) 
</pre>
or not, as wished.

<p/>
The translation routine stores momenta, energies and masses in units 
of GeV, and distances and times in units of mm, with <ei>c = 1</ei>,
exactly as used in PYTHIA. This only works seamlessly for HepMC 2.04
or later, where the choice of units can (and should) be specified in 
the <code>HepMC::GenEvent</code> call. To work also with older HepMC
versions, where normally momenta are stored in MeV, the 
<code>HEPMC_HAS_UNITS</code> environment variable is tested. If not 
defined, i.e. if with an earlier HepMC version, conversion from 
GeV to MeV is done in <code>fill_next_event</code>.

<p/>
The status code is now based on the proposed standard for HepMC 2.05,
see the <aloc href="EventRecord">Event::statusHepMC(...)</aloc> 
conversion routine for details. The earlier behaviour, where all
final particles had status 1 and all initial or intermediate ones 
status 2, is available as a commented-out line in the   
<code>I_Pythia8::fill_next_event(...)</code> method, and so is simple
to recover.

<p/>
In HepMC 2.05 it also becomes possible to store the generated cross 
section and its error. The environment variable
<code>HEPMC_HAS_CROSS_SECTION</code> is used to check whether this
possibility exists and, if it does the current values from 
<code>pythia.info.sigmaGen()</code> and 
<code>pythia.info.sigmaErr()</code> are stored for each event,
multiplied by <ei>10^9</ei> to convert from mb to pb. Note that
PYTHIA improves it accuracy by Monte Carlo integration in the course
of the run, so the values associated with the last generated event
should be the most accurate ones. (If events also come with a dimensional 
weight, like in some Les Houches strategies, conversion from mb to fb 
for that weight must be set by hand, see the last method below.)

<h2>The public methods</h2>

Here comes a complete list of all public methods of the 
<code>I_Pythia8</code> class in the <code>HepMC</code> 
(<i>not</i> <code>Pythia8</code>!) namespace.

<method name="I_Pythia8::I_Pythia8()">
</method>
<methodmore name="virtual I_Pythia8::~I_Pythia8()">
the constructor and destructor take no arguments.
</methodmore>

<method name="bool I_Pythia8::fill_next_event( Pythia8::Pythia& pythia, 
GenEvent* evt, int ievnum = -1, bool convertGluonTo0 = false)">
convert a <code>Pythia</code> event to a <code>HepMC</code> one.
Will return true if succeeded.
<argument name="pythia">
the input <code>Pythia</code> generator object, from which both the 
event and the parton density information can be obtained.
</argument> 
<argument name="evt">
the output <code>GenEvt</code> event, in its standard form.
</argument> 
<argument name="iev">
set the event number of the current event. If negative then the 
internal event number is used, which is incremented by one for
each new event.
</argument>
<argument name="convertGluonTo0">
the normal gluon identity code 21 is used also when parton density
information is stored, unless this optional argument is set true to
have gluons represented by a 0. This choice does not affect the 
normal event record, where a gluon is always 21. 
</argument>
</method>

<method name="bool I_Pythia8::fill_next_event( Pythia8::Event& pyev, 
GenEvent* evt, int ievnum = -1 )">
convert a <code>Pythia</code> event to a <code>HepMC</code> one.
Will return true if succeeded. Do not store parton-density information.
<argument name="pyev">
the input <code>Pythia</code> event, in its standard form.
</argument> 
<argument name="evt">
the output <code>GenEvt</code> event, in its standard form.
</argument> 
<argument name="iev">
set the event number of the current event. If negative then the 
internal event number is used, which is incremented by one for
each new event.
</argument>
</method>

<method name="bool I_Pythia8::put_pdf_info( GenEvent* evt, 
Pythia8::Pythia& pythia, bool convertGluonTo0 = false )">
append parton-density information to an event already stored
by the previous method.
<argument name="evt">
the output <code>GenEvt</code> event record, in its standard form.
</argument> 
<argument name="pythia">
the input <code>Pythia</code> generator object, from which both the 
event and the parton density information can be obtained.
</argument> 
<argument name="convertGluonTo0">
the normal gluon identity code 21 is used also when parton density
information is stored, unless this optional argument is set true to
have gluons represented by a 0. 
</argument>
</method>

<p/>
The following methods can be used to set, and in some cases interrogate,
the status of some switches that can be used to modify the behaviour
of the conversion routine. The <code>set</code> methods have the 
same default input values as the internal initialization ones, so
that a call without an argument (re)stores the default.

<method name="void I_Pythia8::set_trust_mothers_before_daughters( 
bool b = true )">
</method>
<methodmore name="bool I_Pythia8::trust_mothers_before_daughters()">
if there is a conflict in the history information, then trust the 
information on mothers above that on daughters. Currently this is
the only option implemented. 
</methodmore>

<method name="void I_Pythia8::set_trust_both_mothers_and_daughters( 
bool b = false )">
</method>
<methodmore name="bool I_Pythia8::trust_both_mothers_and_daughters()">
currently dummy methods intended to resolve conflicts in the event
history.
</methodmore>

<method name="void I_Pythia8::set_print_inconsistency_errors( 
bool b = true )">
</method>
<methodmore name="bool I_Pythia8::print_inconsistency_errors()">
print a warning line, on <code>cerr</code>, when inconsistent mother 
and daughter information is encountered.
</methodmore>

<method name="void I_Pythia8::set_crash_on_problem( bool b = false )">
if problems are encountered then the run is interrupted by an
<code>exit(1)</code> command. Default is not to crash.
</method>

<method name="void I_Pythia8::set_freepartonwarnings( bool b = true )">
interrupt the run by an <code>exit(1)</code> command if unhadronized 
gluons or quarks are encountered in the event record, unless 
hadronization is switched off. Default is to crash.
</method>

<method name="void I_Pythia8::set_convert_to_mev( bool b = false )">
convert the normal GeV energies, momenta and masses to MeV.
</method>

</chapter>

<!-- Copyright (C) 2012 Torbjorn Sjostrand -->
