<chapter name="QCD Processes">

<h2>QCD Processes</h2>

This section is subdivided into soft and hard QCD processes, with
open charm and bottom production set aside as a special part of the
latter. 

<h3>Soft QCD processes</h3>

As a rule, the processes in this class should not be mixed with
the simulation of other processes. All by themselves, they are
intended to represent the total cross section of hadron collisions,
with the exception of the "rare processes" that one wishes to study
separately. In particular, jet physics at all scales occurs as part 
of the minimum-bias description. 

<p/>
We here use the "minimum bias" expression as a shorthand for 
inelastic, nondiffractive events. Strictly speaking, "minimum bias" 
represents an experimental procedure of accepting "everything", with 
some non-universal cuts to exclude elastic and diffractive topologies. 
In practice, the experimental mimimum-bias sample may then contain
some contamination of what is in PYTHIA classified as diffractive,
especially (high-mass) double diffractive. 

<p/>
Some options to modify these cross sections, and especially to include
Coulomb corrections to the elastic cross section, are found on the
<aloc href="TotalCrossSections">Total Cross Sections</aloc> page.  

<flag name="SoftQCD:all" default="off">
Common switch for the group of all soft QCD processes, 
as listed separately in the following.
</flag>

<flag name="SoftQCD:minBias" default="off">
Minimum-bias events, based on an eikonalized description of all the 
hard QCD processes, so includes them in combinationation with 
low-<ei>pT</ei> events. Code 101.<br/>
Since the current description is handled by the multiple-interactions 
machinery as part of the parton-level processing, no hard process at 
all is defined at the process-level part of the event generation.
Fortunately, in this case a special
<aloc href="EventInformation"><code>codeSub()</code></aloc> 
method provides information on the first, i.e. hardest, subprocess 
selected by the multiple-interactions machinery.

</flag>

<flag name="SoftQCD:elastic" default="off">
Elastic scattering <ei>A B -> A B</ei>.
Code 102.
</flag>

<flag name="SoftQCD:singleDiffractive" default="off">
Single diffractive scattering <ei>A B -> X B</ei> and 
<ei>A B -> A X</ei>. 
Codes 103 and 104.
</flag>

<flag name="SoftQCD:doubleDiffractive" default="off">
Double diffractive scattering <ei>A B -> X_1 X_2</ei>.
Code 105.
</flag>

<h3>Hard QCD processes</h3>

This group contains the processes for QCD jet production above
some minimum <ei>pT</ei> threshold. The <ei>pT_min</ei> cut cannot be put 
too low, or else unreasonably large jet cross sections will be obtained.
An eikonalized description, intended to be valid at all <ei>pT</ei>,
is included as part of the multiple-interactions framework, e.g. in 
<code>SoftQCD:minBias</code> above.
  
<flag name="HardQCD:all" default="off">
Common switch for the group of all hard QCD processes, 
as listed separately in the following.
</flag>

<flag name="HardQCD:gg2gg" default="off">
Scatterings <ei>g g -> g g</ei>.
Code 111.
</flag>

<flag name="HardQCD:gg2qqbar" default="off">
Scatterings <ei>g g -> q qbar</ei>, where <ei>q</ei> by default
is a light quark (<ei>u, d, s</ei>) (see below).
Code 112.
</flag>

<flag name="HardQCD:qg2qg" default="off">
Scatterings <ei>q g -> q g</ei> and <ei>qbar g -> qbar g</ei>.
Code 113.
</flag>

<flag name="HardQCD:qq2qq" default="off">
Scatterings <ei>q q' -> q q'</ei>, <ei>q qbar' -> q qbar'</ei>, 
<ei>qbar qbar' -> qbar qbar'</ei>, where <ei>q'</ei> and <ei>q</ei> 
may agree, but the outgoing flavours equals the incoming ones 
Code 114.
</flag>

<flag name="HardQCD:qqbar2gg" default="off">
Scatterings <ei>q qbar -> g g</ei>. 
Code 115.
</flag>

<flag name="HardQCD:qqbar2qqbarNew" default="off">
Scatterings <ei>q qbar -> q' qbar'</ei>, where <ei>q'</ei> 
by default is a light quark (<ei>u, d, s</ei>) (see below). 
Code 116.
</flag>

<modeopen name="HardQCD:nQuarkNew" default="3" min="0" max="5">
Number of allowed outgoing new quark flavours in the above 
<ei>g g -> q qbar</ei> and <ei>q qbar -> q' qbar'</ei> processes, 
where quarks are treated as massless in the matrix-element expressions 
(but correctly in the phase space). It is thus assumed that <ei>c cbar</ei> 
and <ei>b bbar</ei> are added separately with masses taken into account,
using the processes below. A change to 4 would also include <ei>c cbar</ei> 
in the massless approximation, etc. In order to avoid doublecounting
the processes below should then not be used simultaneously.
</modeopen>

<h3>Hard QCD processes: heavy-flavour subset</h3>

These processes form a natural part of the above class, but can
also be generated separately. Formally the heavy-quark mass makes
these matrix elements finite in the <ei>pT -> 0</ei> limit, but at
high energies one may still question the validity of the expressions
at low <ei>pT</ei> values, like for the other hard-QCD processes.
Also as above, an eikonalized description, intended to be valid at all 
<ei>pT</ei>, is included as part of the multiple-interactions framework. 
<br/>Note that the processes below only represent the "tip of the iceberg"
of charm and bottom production at high energies, where flavour excitation
and shower branchings provide major additional sources. All these sources
come together in the descriptions offered by <code>SoftQCD:minBias</code>
and <code>HardQCD:all</code>.

<flag name="HardQCD:gg2ccbar" default="off">
Scatterings <ei>g g -> c cbar</ei>. 
Code 121.
</flag>

<flag name="HardQCD:qqbar2ccbar" default="off">
Scatterings <ei>q qbar -> c cbar</ei>. 
Code 122.
</flag>

<flag name="HardQCD:gg2bbbar" default="off">
Scatterings <ei>g g -> b bbar</ei>. 
Code 123.
</flag>

<flag name="HardQCD:qqbar2bbbar" default="off">
Scatterings <ei>q qbar -> b bbar</ei>. 
Code 124.
</flag>

</chapter>

<!-- Copyright (C) 2008 Torbjorn Sjostrand -->

